<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>hann.io</title>
    <description>András Hann&#39;s blog showcasing personal projects</description>
    <link>https://hann.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://hann.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 20:36:28 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 20:36:28 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nicely formatted transit schedules</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I enjoy hiking, which most of the times involves using public transportation to get to the start of my hike and to get back home. Planning these trips used to be a major chore in Hungary before 2016, as there was no unified schedule database: one could only plan trips by train &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; bus, not together.  During these times I came up with a timetable format in which I manually collected transit options using the bus and train planner websites as well as a map to came up with potential routes. These days transit information is available via the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/maps/documentation/directions/start&quot;&gt;Google Directions API&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to revisit this format and I developed &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/andrashann/generate-nice-timetables&quot;&gt;a script&lt;/a&gt; that creates it automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://hann.io/articles/2018/nicely-formatted-transit-schedules</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://hann.io/articles/2018/nicely-formatted-transit-schedules</guid>
        
        
        <category>python</category>
        
        <category>transportation</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sunrise, sunset</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I grew up in Budapest and moved to the Netherlands a few years ago. I could not ignore the fact that the Sun has very different patterns: it rises later and sets later here than in Budapest. However, this difference is not uniform: my feeling was that the sun rises much later and sets about the same time during the winter. I saw the inverse in the summer: Dutch summer evenings are much longer, but dawn does not lag behind that much. I wanted to verify this feeling in a scalable manner, so I created a &lt;a href=&quot;http://hann.io/sunrise-sunset/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; (code &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/andrashann/sunrise-sunset&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) where you can pick two arbitrary locations on the globe and see a graph with their dawn/dusk times through the year.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://hann.io/articles/2018/sunrise-sunset</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://hann.io/articles/2018/sunrise-sunset</guid>
        
        
        <category>maps</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>osm</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Where have the camels gone?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.teveclub.hu&quot;&gt;teveclub.hu&lt;/a&gt; used to be one of the most well-known websites among Hungarian teenagers. It is a Neopets clone where you can raise your own camel: feed it, and teach it various tricks day by day. I had the feeling that the site was slowly dying. I used data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/web/&quot;&gt;archive.org&lt;/a&gt; to verify this hypothesis and I found that it was true: the total number of camels in the system has dropped from the ~320 thousand peak in 2006 to less than 26 thousand in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://hann.io/articles/2016/where-have-the-camels-gone</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://hann.io/articles/2016/where-have-the-camels-gone</guid>
        
        
        <category>hungary</category>
        
        <category>graph</category>
        
        <category>python</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Grab a drink while you wait for the bus</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I always found it fascinating that there are several bus stops in Hungary which are called “{municipality name}, Cooperative Liquor Store” (&lt;em&gt;szövetkezeti italbolt&lt;/em&gt; in Hungarian). It might get somewhat lost in translation that such a name very much reminds the reader of the socialist era it was given to the bus stop.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://hann.io/articles/2015/grab-a-drink-while-you-wait-for-the-bus</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://hann.io/articles/2015/grab-a-drink-while-you-wait-for-the-bus</guid>
        
        
        <category>hungary</category>
        
        <category>maps</category>
        
        <category>openstreetmap</category>
        
        <category>transportation</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hungarian municiaplity name prefixes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hungarian municipalities have unique names that consist of one (potentially compound) word. This was not the case until the end of the 19th century: multiple villages could have the same name, sometimes even in the same county. This caused trouble not only for the postal service but also related to taxation and conscription. Hence the standardization: every name must be unique; in case of a duplcate, the municipality names got a prefix based on their general location. I investigated these prefixes: their spatial distribution and the origin of those names.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://hann.io/articles/2015/hungarian-munipality-name-prefixes</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://hann.io/articles/2015/hungarian-munipality-name-prefixes</guid>
        
        
        <category>maps</category>
        
        <category>hungary</category>
        
        <category>openstreetmap</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bad idea of the day: toll on M0, the ring road around Budapest</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20180513180658/http://nol.hu/gazdasag/fizetos-lesz-az-m0-s-1503659&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; published yesterday in &lt;em&gt;Népszabadság&lt;/em&gt; reveals that the Hungarian budget for 2015 includes a proposal to introduce tolls on several motorway segments that are toll-free today. To me, this sounds like a bad idea.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://hann.io/articles/2014/bad-idea-tolled-m0</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://hann.io/articles/2014/bad-idea-tolled-m0</guid>
        
        
        <category>transportation</category>
        
        <category>hungary</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How far up does the tram go?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Historically, there were three relatively hilly tram lines in Budapest: 58, 59, and 61.&lt;label for=&quot;sn-id-trams&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sn-id-trams&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt; Service on line 58 has been suspended since 1977. In this case, “suspension” includes the tracks having been removed and paved over. Based on this, I do not think service will restart anytime soon. &lt;/span&gt; But how far up do these actually go? And which one is the steepest?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://hann.io/articles/2013/how-far-up-does-the-tram-go</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://hann.io/articles/2013/how-far-up-does-the-tram-go</guid>
        
        
        <category>maps</category>
        
        <category>hungary</category>
        
        <category>transportation</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Revolutionary street names</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Every Hungarian knows that almost every village in the country will have a street named after Lajos Kossuth, revolutionary and politician, and another named after Sándor Petőfi, an emblematic hero-poet – both of whom took part in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hungarian_Revolution_of_1848&quot;&gt;Hungarian Revolution of 1848&lt;/a&gt;. But where exactly are these streets?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://hann.io/articles/2013/revolutionary-street-names</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://hann.io/articles/2013/revolutionary-street-names</guid>
        
        
        <category>maps</category>
        
        <category>hungary</category>
        
        <category>openstreetmap</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
